Finding Aid for English Language Institute (University of Michigan) Records, 1940-2004
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
- Administrative Files 1952-2005
  - Budget Memoranda 1976 (Box 10)
  - Catford, John C. (Colloquia) (Box 10)
  - Civil Liberties Board Questionnaires
    - Memoranda and Proposals 1964-1967 (Box 10)
  - Contrastive Analysis Project Reports 1968-1969 (Box 10)
  - Coordinator's Committee 1952-1965
    - Minutes and Agendas 1963-1965 (Box 10)
    - Reports-International Teachers of English 1952-1958 (Box 10)
    - Reports 1963-1970 (Box 10)
  - Curriculum Development Committee
    - Minutes and Memoranda 1976-1977 (Box 10)
  - Director Search circa 1996 (Box 10)
  - Director's Reports 1956-1960 (Box 10)
  - Executive Committee 1956-1975
    - Memoranda, Correspondence, Minutes 1956-1960 (Box 10)
    - Memoranda and Minutes 1975 (Box 10)
    - Minutes 2005 (Box 10)
  - Extension Service
    - Correspondence and Memoranda 1960-1962 (Box 10)
  - Instructional Materials
    - General Materials 1963-1964 (Box 10)
    - 15-week Extension Course 1966 (Box 10)
    - Phonetics Course undated (Box 10)
  - Internal Report of English Language Institute 1999 (Box 10)
  - Library Statements and Reports 2002-2004 (Box 10)
  - Long-Term Plan August 2004 (Box 10)
    (see also: Vision Document)
  - Marckwardt, Albert H. (Correspondence) 1959-1961 (Box 10)
  - NAFSA (Correspondence and other Materials) 1969 (Box 10)
  - Non-discrimination Compliance Reports 1964-1967 (Box 10)
  - Oswald, Marina (Box 10)
  - Papers and Speeches
    - Official 1964-1968 (Box 10)
    - Personal 1959 (Box 10)
  - Publicity
    - 1956 (Box 10)
    - 1960-1965 (Box 10)
  - Regents Proceedings and Material (Box 10)
  - Reports, Miscellaneous 1981-1982 (Box 10)
  - Reports, Miscellaneous 2002-2003 (Box 10)
  - Research Administration 1960-1962 (Box 10)
  - Residence Hall Material 1956-1973 (Box 10)
  - Search Committee-Memoranda 1974-1975 (Box 11)
  - Small Contracts Proposal 1965-1966 (Box 11)
  - Staff Meeting Minutes 1990-2001, 2003-2005, 8 folders (Box 11)
  - Staffing and Internal Reports 1956-1961 (Box 11)
  - Student Enrollment 1966-1972 (Box 11)
  - Student Essays and Evaluations 1956 (Box 11)
  - Student Loan Fund 1958-1960 (Box 11)
  - Testing Meeting Minutes 2005 (Box 11)
  - Vision Document 2003 (Box 11)
    (see also: Long-Term Plan)
- South East Asia Regional English Project (SEAREP) 1958-1964
  The South East Asia Regional English Project (SEAREP) (1958-1964, 6.5 linear ft.) contains records from one of ELI's most extensive international language programs. Two subseries are present. The Campus Coordinator Office subseries primarily contains files on the administrative side of the project with personnel and correspondence. The Project Office subseries focuses more on the project in action with proposals, reports, and materials from the various South East Asian countries involved, including Burma, Cambodia, Laos, Indonesia, Vietnam and Thailand.
  - Campus Coordinator Office
    - Address, telephone list (Box 11)
    - Agencies related to English training (Box 11)
    - Audit report, Thailand 1964 (Box 11)
    - Contract (Box 11)
    - Contract extensions (Box 11)
    - Contract termination (Box 11)
    - Correspondence, alphabetical 1959-1963 (Box 11)
    - Correspondence, chronological 1961 (Box 11)
    - Correspondence, by individual
      - Anthony, Edward M.
        - 1959 (Box 11)
        - 1960-1964 (Box 11)
      - Campbell, Russell N. (Box 11)
      - Chandler, James B. (Box 11)
      - Fraser, Roderick D. (Box 11)
      - Huskey, Stanley G. (Box 11)
      - Loveless, Owen (Box 11)
      - McKinley, Barbara I. (Box 11)
      - Stacey, William A. (Box 11)
      - Van Syoc, W. Bryce (Box 11)
      - Weir, W.T. (Box 12)
      - Wigfield, Jack W. (Box 12)
      - Yates, Warren G.
        - 1958-1960 (Box 12)
        - 1961 (Box 12)
        - 1962-1964 (Box 12)
    - English Language Institute (Box 12)
    - English language tapes (Box 12)
    - Hatcher visit to South East Asia (Box 12)
    - Personnel
      - Anthony, Edward M. (Box 12)
      - Blecha, Evelyn J. (Box 12)
      - Campbell, Russell N. (Box 12)
      - Chandler, James B. (Box 12)
      - Clubb, Merrel D. (Box 12)
      - Durling, Donald H. (Box 12)
      - Forsyte, John T. (Box 12)
    - Personnel (cont.)
      - Huskey, Stanley G. (Box 12)
      - Jones, Hartley (Box 12)
      - Kriedler, Carol K. (Box 12)
      - Lado, Robert (Box 12)
      - Loveless, Owen (Box 12)
      - Luther, George E. (Box 12)
      - McBeth, Lloyd S. (Box 12)
      - McKinley, Barbara I. (Box 12)
      - Manoroth, Phengsy (Box 12)
      - Marckwardt, Albert H. (Box 12)
      - Murphy, Irene E. (Box 12)
      - Plaister, Theodore H. (Box 12)
      - Rejas, Pauline M. (Box 12)
      - Russell, Doris M.P. (Box 12)
      - Sanders, Gerald A. (Box 12)
      - Stacey, William A. (Box 12)
      - Strozzi, Roy R. (Box 12)
      - Thompson, Lionel G. (Box 12)
      - Van Syoc, W. Bryce (Box 12)
      - Wigfield, Jack W. (Box 12)
      - Wohl, Milton (Box 12)
      - Yates, Warren G. (Box 12)
    - Personnel, clerical
      - Bailey, Betty S. (Box 12)
      - Chopp, Marjorie A. (Box 12)
      - Conners, N. Jeanne (Box 12)
      - Corey, Helen M. (Box 12)
      - Kugler, Ruth M. (Box 12)
      - Leetsma, Margaret B. (Box 12)
      - Sariputra, Tulaya (Box 12)
      - Miscellaneous (Box 12)
    - Personnel, miscellaneous (Box 12)
    - Procedures, new staff (Box 12)
    - Project visitors to campus (Box 12)
    - SEAREP, Evaluation of contractor's performance 1958-1961 (Box 12)
    - Songs (Box 12)
  - Project Office
    - Aural comprehension tests (Box 13)
    - Burma Program 1961 (Box 13)
    - Cambodia (Box 13)
    - Class schedules (Box 13)
    - Correspondence 1958-1962 (Box 13)
    - Correspondence, Campus Coordinator
      - October 1958-December 1959 (Box 13)
      - 1960 (Box 13)
      - 1962 (Box 13)
      - 1963 (Box 13)
      - 1964 (Box 13)
    - Correspondence, chronological
      - 1958 (Box 13)
      - January-June 1959 (Box 13)
      - July-December 1959 (Box 13)
      - January-June 1960 (Box 13)
      - July-December 1960 (Box 13)
      - January-June 1961 (Box 13)
      - July-December 1961 (Box 13)
      - January-June 1962 (Box 13)
      - July-December 1962 (Box 13)
      - January-June 1963 (Box 13)
      - July-December 1963 (Box 13)
      - January-June 1964 (Box 13)
    - Correspondence, Regional Project in Education (Box 14)
    - Correspondence, Van Syoc (Box 14)
    - Education Agreement, France/Laos (Box 14)
    - English Language Committee (Box 14)
    - English language testing, Thailand (Box 14)
    - File arrangement (Box 14)
    - Finance (Box 14)
    - History (Box 14)
    - Indonesia English Language Project 1960 (Box 14)
    - Language laboratories (Box 14)
    - Laos
      - Correspondence
        - 1958-1959 (Box 14)
        - 1959-1960 (Box 14)
        - 1960 (Box 14)
        - 1961 (Box 14)
        - 1962-1964 (Box 14)
      - Education system (Box 14)
      - Emergency evacuation (Box 14)
      - Monthly reports 1959-1964 (Box 14)
    - Materials Preparation (Box 14)
    - Materials Preparation, Ad Hoc Committee (Box 14)
    - Office costs (Box 14)
    - Personnel, annual and sick leave (Box 14)
    - Personnel clearance notices (Box 14)
    - Personnel, by individual
      - Campbell, Russell N. (Box 15)
      - Durling, Donald H. (Box 15)
      - Huskey, Stanley G. (Box 15)
      - McBeth, Lloyd S. (Box 15)
      - McKinley, Barbara I. (Box 15)
      - Sanders, Gerald A. (Box 15)
      - Strozzi, Roy R. (Box 15)
      - Thompson, Lionel G. (Box 15)
      - Wohl, Milton (Box 15)
      - Yates, Warren G. (Box 15)
    - Personnel, local (Box 15)
    - Project agreements (budgets) 1957-1962 (Box 15)
    - Project audit (Box 15)
    - Project evaluation summary (Box 15)
    - Project proposals (Box 15)
    - Project review 1959, 1960 (Box 15)
    - Publications; education materials (Box 15)
    - Public relations (Box 15)
    - Regional Conference, Vietnam 1961 (Box 15)
    - Regional Conference, Thailand 1960 (Box 15)
    - Regional English Project Joint Committee (Box 15)
    - Reports
      - Annual, semi-annual August 1958-September 1963 (Box 15)
      - Summary Monthly, 1st to 66th month 1958-1964 (Box 15)
      - Summary Quarterly, Summary Semi-Annual (Box 15)
      - Summary Report, Final 1963 (Box 15)
    - Seminars, miscellaneous (Box 15)
    - Special Course for Teachers of English (Box 15)
    - Staff meetings (Box 15)
    - Staffing (Box 15)
    - Teacher training, Thailand, Laos, Cambodia (Box 15)
    - Telegrams
      - 1958-1960 (Box 15)
      - 1961-1962 (Box 15)
      - 1963-1964 (Box 15)
    - Textbook loan collection (Box 15)
    - Thailand (Box 16)
      - Educational organization (Box 16)
      - Ministry of Education 1961-1964
        - Department of Secondary Education (Box 16)
        - Department of Teacher Training 1958-1964 (Box 16)
        - Department of Teacher Training counterpart funds (Box 16)
        - Department of Vocational Education (Box 16)
      - Teacher training colleges (Box 16)
      - Technical and Economic Cooperation Department (TTEC) (Box 16)
    - Typewriters (Box 16)
    - United States. Agency for International Development
      - United States Operations Mission to Thailand (USOM) (Box 16)
      - Administrative notices, allowances (Box 16)
      - Education Program 1958-1962 (Box 16)
      - Office memos 1960-1963 (Box 16)
      - Participant training program (Box 17)
      - Policy orders, staff notices (Box 17)
    - United States. Peace Corps. 1961-1962 (Box 17)
    - Vehicles (Box 17)
    - Vietnam
      - Annual report 1960-1961 (Box 17)
      - Correspondence
        - 1959-1960 (Box 17)
        - 1961 (Box 17)
        - 1962 (Box 17)
        - 1963 (Box 17)
      - Lesson plans, Hoa Secondary Materials (Box 17)
      - Monthly reports 1959-April 1963 (Box 17)
      - Problems (Box 17)
    - Visitors (Box 17)
    - Photographs
      (see also: Photographs in Box 19)
      - Prints
        - Cambodia (Box 17)
        - Laos (Box 17)
        - SEAREP (Box 17)
        - SEAREP staff (Box 17)
        - Thailand (Box 17)
        - Vietnam (Box 17)
      - Negatives
        - Laos (Box 17)
        - SEAREP (Box 17)
- Ford-Japan Project 1959-1964
  The Ford-Japan Project series (1959-1964, .7 linear ft.) represents another ELI language program in conjunction with Japanese universities and the Ford Foundation. The series includes correspondence, project reports and proposals, scholarships, and files on several Japanese universities.
  - Advisory Committee on the Training of Teachers of English in Selected Japanese Universities (ACTT) 1959-1964 (Box 18)
  - Budget control reports (Box 18)
  - Budgets (Box 18)
  - Correspondence
    - Anthony, Edward M. (Box 18)
    - Ford Foundation 1959-1961 (Box 18)
    - Ford Foundation, Everton, John S. (Box 18)
    - General (Box 18)
    - International House of Japan (Box 18)
    - Lado, Robert (Box 18)
    - McCarus, Ernest N. (Box 18)
    - Marckwardt, Albert H. (Box 18)
  - Fulbright Commission, Japan (Box 18)
  - Language laboratories (Box 18)
  - Project proposal 1959-1961 (Box 18)
  - Project proposals, other (Box 18)
  - Project report, Final 1959-1964 (Box 18)
  - Project report, interim (Box 18)
  - Scholarships and Fellowships
    - general 1959-1964 (Box 18)
    - 1959-1960 (Box 18)
    - 1960-1961 (Box 18)
    - 1961-1962 (Box 18)
    - 1962-1963 (Box 18)
    - 1963-1964 (Box 18)
  - Universities, Japan
    - Hiroshima University (Box 18)
    - International Christian University (Box 18)
    - Keio University (Box 18)
    - Kobe City University of Foreign Studies (Box 18)
    - Kyoto University (Box 18)
    - Kyushu University (Box 18)
    - Osaka University (Box 18)
    - Otaru University of Commerce (Box 18)
    - Sophia University (Box 18)
    - Tohoku University (Box 18)
    - Tokyo University of Education (Box 18)
    - Tokyo University of Foreign Studies (Box 18)
    - Tsuda College (Box 18)
    - University of Tokyo. Faculty of Letters (Box 18)
    - Waseda University (Box 18)
- Publications 1941-2003
  The Publications series (1941-2003, .3 linear ft.) contains items published by the ELI including early student publications, brochures, teaching materials, and newsletters.
  - Early ELI Publications 1941-1956 (Box 18)
  - ELI Publication Lists, Promotional Materials, and Brochures, undated 1973-2003 (Box 18)
  - Newsletters 2003 (Box 18)
- Photographs undated
  The Photographs series contains (undated, .3 linear ft.) photographs, ca.1940-1970, relating to the activities of the English Language Institute. The series includes pictures of instruction, conferences, visitors, faculty, foreign students and social activities.
  - Photographs (Box 19)
    (see also: Photographs in Box 17)
    - Ann Arbor School program, "World Neighbors" (Box 19)
    - Classes and classroom shots (Box 19)
    - Faculty and Staff (Box 19)
    - Groups (identified) (Box 19)
    - Groups (unidentified) (Box 19)
    - Indian (East) program (Box 19)
    - Japanese program (Box 19)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 19)
    - Scrapbooks (Box 19)
      (in Box 7)
    - Social Activities (Box 19)
Related Materials
Researchers interested in the English Language Institute Records may also be interested in the Ruth Hok Papers at the Bentley Historical Library, the Coordinator's report: International teachers of English, Fall 1954, and various serials also held at the Bentley: The Ann Arbor Diary, Language and Learning, International Teachers of English-English Language Institute, and English language institute at the University of Michigan for Latin-American students and teachers of English. The journal Language and Learning is also in the holdings of the Hatcher Graduate Library and the Shapiro Undergraduate Library. Also of interest at the Bentley are: Lessons in pronunciation by the research staff of the English Language Institute and the publication, Intensive Course in English for Latin American students (call no.: FImu B27 .E58 A4).